Chapter 133.
The chase. First day.
That night in the midwatch, when the old man, as his want at intervals, stepped
forth from the scuttle in which he leaned, and went to his pivot hole, he
suddenly thrust his face out fiercely, snuffing up the sea air, as a sagacious
ship's dog will, in drawing nigh to some barbarous aisle. He declared that a
whale must be near. Soon that peculiar odor, sometimes to a great distance
given forth by the living sperm whale, was palpable to all the watch. Nor was
any mariner surprised when, after inspecting the compass, and then the dog
vein, and then ascertaining the precise bearing of the odor as nearly as
possible, Ahab rapidly ordered the ship's course to be slightly altered,
and the sail to be shortened. The acute policy dictating these movements was
sufficiently vindicated at daybreak by the sight of a long sleek on the sea
directly and lengthwise ahead, smooth as oil, and resembling in the pleated
watery wrinkles bordering it the polished metallic-like marks of some
swift tide rip at the mouth of a deep rapid stream.
Man the mast heads, call all hands.
Thundering with the butts of three clubbed hand spikes on the folks deck,
Dagu roused the sleepers with such judgment claps that they seemed to exhale from the scuttle so
instantaneously did they appear with their clothes in their hands. "What do
you see?" cried Ahab, flattening his face to the sky. "Nothing, nothing,
sir," was the sound hailing down in reply. to gallant sails, stunils, a low
and a loft, and on both sides.
All sail being set, he now cast loose the lifeline reserved for swaying him to
the main royal mast head, and in a few moments they were hoisting him thither,
when, while 2/3 of the way aloft, and while peering ahead through the
horizontal vacancy between the main tops and the tag gallant sail, he raised a
gull-like cry in the air. There she blows. There she blows. A hump like a
snow hill. It is Moby Dick.
Fired by the cry which seemed simultaneously taken up by the three
lookouts, the men on deck rushed to the rigging to behold the famous whale they
had so long been pursuing. Ahab had now gained his final perch some feet above
the other lookouts. Tashego standing just beneath him on the cap of the tag
gallant mast so that the Indian's head was almost on a level with Ahab's heel.
From this height the whale was now seen some mile or so ahead at every roll of
the sea revealing his high sparkling hump and regularly jetting his silent
spout into the air. To the credulous mariners it seemed the same silent spout
they had so long ago beheld in the moonlit Atlantic and Indian oceans. And
did none of you see it before? Cried Ahab, hailing the perched men all around
him. I saw him almost that same instant, sir, that Captain Ahab did, and I cried
out, said Tashego.
Not the same instant. Not the same. No, the deon is mine. Fate reserved the
deloon for me. I only none of you could have raised the white whale first. There
she blows. There she blows. There she blows. There again. There again, he
cried out in long drawn lingering methodic tones attuned to the gradual
prolongings of the whales visible jets.
He's going to sound in stencils down to gallant sails. Stand by the three boats.
Mr. Starbucks remembers stay on board and keep the ship helm there. Luff luff
a point. So, steady man, steady. There go flukes. No, no, only black water.
Already the boat's there. Stand by.
Stand by. Lower me, Mr. Starbucks.
Lower. Lower. Quick. Quicker. And he slid through the air to the deck. He's
heading straight to Lurard, sir, cried Stub. Right away from us. Cannot have
seen the ship yet. Be dumb, man. Stand by the braces. hard down the helm. Brace
up. Shiver her. Shiver her. So well that. Boats. Boats.
Soon all the boats but Starbucks were dropped. All the boat sails set. All the
paddles pllying with rippling swiftness shooting to lure and Ahab heading the
onset. A pale death glimmer lit up Fidala's sunken eyes. A hideous motion
nawed his mouth. Like noless nautilus shells. Their light prows sped through
the sea, but only slowly they neared the foe. As they neared him, the ocean grew
still more smooth, seemed drawing a carpet over its waves, seemed a noon
meadow so serenely it spread. At length the breathless hunter came so nigh his
seemingly unsuspecting prey that his entire dazzling hump was distinctly
visible sliding along the sea as if an isolated thing and continually set in a
revolving ring of finest fleecy greenish foam. He saw the vast involved wrinkles
of the slightly projecting head beyond.
Before it, far out on the soft Turkish rugged waters, went the glistening white
shadow from his broad milky forehead, a musical rippling playfully accompanying
the shade, and behind the blue waters interchangeably flowed over into the
moving valley of his steady wake. And on either hand bright bubbles arose and
danced by his side. But these were broken again by the light toes of
hundreds of gay fowl softly feathering the sea, alternate with their fitful
flight, and like to some flag staff rising from the painted hull of an
Argusy, the tall but shattered pole of a recent lance projected from the white
whale's back, and at intervals one of the cloud of soft toaded fowls hovering,
and to fro skimming like a canopy over the fish, silently perched and rocked on
this pole, the long tail feathers streaming like penins. A gentle
joyousness, a mighty mildness of repose and swiftness invested the gliding
whale, not the white bull Jupiter swimming away with ravished Europa
clinging to his graceful horns, his lovely learing eyes sideways intent upon
the maid with smooth bewitching fleetness rippling straight for the
nuptial bower in cree. Not Jove, not that great majesty supreme did surpass
the glorified whale as he so divinely swam.
On each soft side, coincident with the parted swell, that but once leaving him
then flowed so wide away. On each bright side the whale shed off enticings. No
wonder there had been some among the hunters who, namelessly transported and
allured by all this serenity, had ventured to assail it, but had fatally
found that quietude but the vesture of tornadoes. Yet calm, enticing calm, oh
whale, thou glidest on to all who for the first time eye thee, no matter how
many in that same way thou mayest have be juggled and destroyed before. And
thus, through the serene tranquilities of the tropical sea, among waves whose
hand clappings were suspended by exceeding rapture, Moby Dick moved on,
still withholding from sight the full terrors of his submerged trunk, entirely
hiding the wrenched hideousness of his jaw. But soon the forart of him slowly
rose from the water. For an instant his whole marbleized body formed a high arch
like Virginia's natural bridge, and warningly waving his bannered flukes in
the air, the grand god revealed himself, sounded, and went out of sight.
Hoveringly halting and dipping on the wing, the white sea fowls longingly
lingered over the agitated pool that he left. With ores a peak and paddles down,
the sheets of their sails a drift, the three boats now stillly floated,
awaiting Moby Dick's reappearance.
"An hour," said Ahab, standing rooted in his boat's stern, and he gazed beyond
the whale's place towards the dim blue spaces and wide wooing vacancies to
lure. It was only an instant, for again his eyes seemed whirling round in his
head as he swept the watery circle. The breeze now freshened. The sea began to
swell. The birds, the birds, cried Tashego.
In long Indian file, as when herand take wing, the white birds were now all
flying towards Ahab's boat, and when within a few yards began fluttering over
the water there, wheeling round and round with joyous, expectant cries.
Their vision was keener than man's. Ahab could discover no sign in the sea, but
suddenly, as he peered down and down into its depths, he profoundly saw a
white living spot no bigger than a white weasel, with wonderful solarity
uprising, and magnifying as it rose, till it turned, and then there were
plainly revealed two long, crooked rows of white, glistening teeth, floating up
from the undiscoverable bottom. It was Moby Dick's open mouth and scrolled jaw,
his vast shadowed bulk still half blending with the blue of the sea. The
glittering mouth yawned beneath the boat like an open-ed marble tomb, and giving
one sidelong sweep with his steering ore, Ahab whirled the craft aside from
this tremendous apparition. Then calling upon Fidala to change places with him,
went forward to the boughs, and seizing Perth's harpoon commanded his crew to
grasp their oars and stand by to stern.
Now by reason of this timely spinning round the boat upon its axis, its bow by
anticipation was made to face the whale's head while yet underwater. But
as if perceiving this strategim, Moby Dick, with that malicious intelligence
ascribed to him, sidlingly transplanted himself, as it were, in an instant,
shooting his pleated head lengthwise beneath the boat. Through and through,
through every plank and each rib, it thrilled for an instant, the whale,
obliquely lying on his back, in the manner of a biting shark, slowly and
feelingly taking its boughs full within his mouth, so that the long narrow
scrolled lower jaw curled high up into the open air, and one of the teeth
caught in a rowlock. The bluish pearl white of the inside of the jaw was
within six inches of Ahab's head and reached higher than that. In this
attitude, the white whale now shook the slight cedar as a mildly cruel cat her
mouse. With unstonished eyes, Fidala gazed and crossed his arms, but the
tiger yellow crew were tumbling over each other's heads to gain the uttermost
stern. And now, while both elastic gunnels were springing in and out, while
the whale dallied with the doomed craft in this devilish way, and from his body
being submerged beneath the boat, he could not be darted at from the boughs,
for the boughs were almost inside of him, as it were, and while the other
boats involuntarily paused, as before a quick crisis impossible to withstand,
then it was that monomomaniac Ahab, furious with this tantalizing vicinity
of his foe, which placed him all alive and helpless in the very jaws he hated.
Frenzied with all this, he seized the long bone with his naked hands, and
wildly strove to wrench it from its grip. As now he thus vainly strove, the
jaw slipped from him. The frail gunnels bent in, collapsed, and snapped as both
jaws, like an enormous shears, sliding further aft, bit the craft completely in
twain, and locked themselves fast again in the sea, midway between the two
floating wrecks. These floated aside, the broken ends drooping, the crew at
the stern wreck clinging to the gunnels, and striving to hold fast to the oars to
lash them across.
At that preluding moment, air the boat was yet snapped. Ahab, the first to
perceive the whale's intent by the crafty upraising of his head, a movement
that loosed his hold for the time. At that moment his hand made one final
effort to push the boat out of the bite, but only slipping further into the
whale's mouth, and tilting over sideways as it slipped. The boat had shaken off
his hold on the jaw, spilled him out of
it as he leaned to the push, and so he fell flat-faced upon the sea.
Ripplingly withdrawing from his prey, Moby Dick now lay at a little distance,
vertically thrusting his oblong white head up and down in the billows, and at
the same time slowly revolving his whole spindled body, so that when his vast
wrinkled forehead rose some 20 or more feet out of the water, the now rising
swells, with all their confluent waves, dazzlingly broke against it,
vindictively tossing their shivered spray still higher in the air. So in a
gale the but half baffled channel billows only recoil from the base of the
eddy stone triumphantly to over leap its summit with their scud.
Footnote this motion is peculiar to the sperm whale. It receives its designation
pitch polling from its being likened to that preliminary up and down poise of
the whale lance in the exercise called pitch polling previously described. By
this motion, the whale must best and most comprehensively view whatever
objects may be encircling him. End of footnote.
But soon resuming his horizontal attitude, Moby Dick swam swiftly round
and round the wrecked crew, sideways, churning the water in his vengeful wake,
as if lashing himself up to still another and more deadly assault. The
sight of the splintered boat seemed to madden him as the blood of grapes and
mulberries cast before Antiochus's elephants in the book of Mcabes.
Meanwhile, Ahab, half smothered in the foam of the whale's insulent tail, and
too much of a to swim, though he could still keep afloat even in the
heart of such a whirlpool as that.
Helpless Ahab's head was seen like a tossed bubble which the least chance
shock might burst. From the boat's fragmentaryary stern, Fidala incuriously
and mildly eyed him. The clinging crew at the other drifting end could not
sucker him. More than enough was it for them to look to themselves, for so
revolvingly appalling was the white whale's aspect, and so planetarily swift
the ever contracting circles he made, that he seemed horizontally swooping
upon them. And though the other boats, unharmed, still hovered hard by, still
they dared not pull into the eddy to strike, lest that should be the signal
for the instant destruction of the jeopardized castaways, Ahab and all. Nor
in that case could they themselves hope to escape. With straining eyes then they
remained on the outer edge of the direhole zone whose center had now become the old man's head.
Meantime from the beginning all this had been described from the ship's mast
heads and squaring her yards she had worn down upon the scene and was now so
nigh that Ahab in the water hailed her.
sail on the But that moment a breaking sea dashed on him from Moby Dick and
wellelmed him for the time. But struggling out of it again and chancing
to rise on the towering crest, he shouted, "Sail on the whale. Drive him
off." The Peekquad's prows were pointed, and breaking up the charmed circle, she
effectually parted the white whale from his victim. As he sullenly swam off, the
boats flew to the rescue. dragged into Stub's boat with bloodshot blinded eyes,
the white brine caking in his wrinkles, the long tension of Ahab's bodily
strength did crack, and helplessly he yielded to his body's doom. For a time,
lying all crushed in the bottom of Stub's boat, like one trotten underfoot
of herds of elephants. Far inland nameless whales came from him, as
desolate sounds from out ravines.
But this intensity of his physical prostration did but so much the more
abbreviate it. In an instant compass great hearts sometimes condensed to one
deep pang the sum total of those shallow pains kindly diffuse through feebler
men's whole lives. And so such hearts, though summary in each one suffering,
still if the gods decree it, in their lifetime aggregate a whole age of woe,
wholly made up of instantaneous intensities, for even in their pointless
centers, those noble natures contain the entire circumferences of inferior souls.
The harpoon, said Ahab, halfway rising and draggingly leaning on one bended
arm. Is it safe? I sir, for it was not darted. This is it, said Stub, showing
it. Lay it before me. Any missing men. 1
2 3 4 5. There were five ores, sir. And here are five men. That's good. Help me,
man. I wish to stand. So, so I see him there. There. Going to lure still. What
a leaping spout. Hands off from me. The eternal sap runs up in Ahab's bones
again. Set the sail outs the helm.
It is often the case that when a boat is stove, its crew being picked up by
another boat helped to work that second boat, and the chase is thus continued
with what is called doublebanked oars.
It was thus now. But the added power of the boat did not equal the added power
of the whale, for he seemed to have treble bananked his every fin, swimming
with a velocity which plainly showed that if now under these circumstances
pushed on, the chase would prove an indefinitely prolonged, if not a
hopeless one, nor could any crew endure for so long a period such an
unintermitted, intense straining at the ore, a thing barely tolerable only in
some one brief bicissitude. The ship itself, then, as it sometimes happens,
offered the most promising intermediate means of overtaking the chase.
Accordingly, the boats now made for her, and were soon swayed up to their cranes,
the two parts of the wrecked boat having been previously secured by her, and then
hoisting everything to her side, and stacking her canvas high up, and
sideways outstretching it with stun souls like the double-jointed wings of
an albatross, the Peekquad bore down in the lured wake of Moby Dick. At the
well-known methodic intervals the whale's glittering spout was regularly
announced from the manned mast heads, and when he would be reported as just
gone down, Ahab would take the time, and then pacing the deck, binnacle watch in
hand, so soon as the last second of the allotted hour expired, his voice was
heard. Who's as the deloon now? Do you see him? And if the reply was, "No,
sir," straightway he commanded them to lift him to his perch. In this way the
day wore on, Ahab now aloft and motionless, Anon unrestingly pacing the
planks. As he was thus walking, uttering no sound except to hail the men aloft,
or to bid them hoist a sail still higher, or to spread one to a still
greater breadth, thus to and fro pacing beneath his slouched hat. At every turn
he passed his own wrecked boat, which had been dropped upon the quarter deck,
and lay there reversed, broken bow to shattered stern. At last he paused
before it, and as in an already overclouded sky fresh troops of clouds
will sometimes sail across, so over the old man's face there now stole some such
outed gloom as this. Stub saw him pause, and perhaps intending, not vainly,
though, to evce his own unabated fortitude, and thus keep up a valiant
place in his captain's mind, he advanced, and eyeing the wreck,
exclaimed, "The thistle!" the ass refused. It pricricked his mouth too keenly, "Sir,
what soulless thing is this that laughs before a wreck? Man, man,
did I not know thee brave as fearless fire and as mechanical? I could swear
thou w to poultrune. Groan nor laugh should be heard before a wreck.
I I sir, said Starbucks, drawing near.
It is a solemn sight. An omen and an ill one. Omen. Omen. The dictionary. If the
gods think to speak outright to man, they will honorably speak outright, not
shake their heads and give an old wives darkling hint. Be gone. Ye too are the
opposite poles of one thing. Starbucks is stub reversed, and Stub is Starbucks,
and ye too are all mankind. And Ahab stands alone among the millions of the
people earth, nor gods, nor men his neighbors.
Cold, cold, I shiver.
How now a loft there? Do you see him?
Sing out for every spout, though he spout 10 times a second.
The day was nearly done. Only the hem of his golden robe was rustling. Soon it
was almost dark, but the lookout men still remained unset.
"Can't see the spout now, sir. Too dark," cried a voice from the air. How
heading when last seen as before, sir.
Straight to Lurard. Good. He will travel slower now it is night. Down royals and
to gallon stencils, Mr. Starbucks. We must not run over him before morning.
He's making a passage now and may heave too a while. Helm there. Keep her full
before the wind. A loft. Come down. Mr.
stub send a fresh hand to the four mast head and see it manned till morning.
Then advancing toward the deloon in the main mast. Men, this gold is mine, for I
earned it, but I shall let it abide here till the white whale is dead. And then
whosoever of you first raises him, upon the day he shall be killed, this gold is
that man's. And if on that day I shall again raise him, then 10 times its sum
shall be divided among all of you. Away now the deck is thine, sir.
And so saying, he placed himself halfway within the scuttle, and slouching his
hat, stood there till dawn, except when, at intervals, rousing himself to see how
the night wore on.